Finding Aid for Florence R. Crane papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Florence R. Crane Papers 1949-1989
Crane, Florence R. (1911 - )
1 linear foot and 1 oversize folder
90168 Aa 2 Ac
Republican member of the Ann Arbor, Michigan City Council, 1957-1961; active participant in civic and political affairs on the state and local level. Subject files relating to her involvement with various civic and community organizations.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Florence R. Crane (Donor No. 7622 ) in November 1988 and March 1989.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Florence R. Crane was born in 1911. She received her bachelor's degree from the University of California at Los Angeles. Crane and her husband, Dr. H. R. Crane, University of Michigan Professor of Physics, moved to Ann Arbor, Michigan in 1935.
Crane was active in civic and political affairs on the state and local levels. She served as Publicity Chair and Executive Committee Chair of the Ann Arbor Citizens' Council and as Chair of the Citizen's Housing Committee, 1953-1955. She served on the Ann Arbor City Republican Committee (Chair, 1954-55). She was Ann Arbor City Councilwoman, 1957-1961. She was appointed to the Michigan State Corrections Commission and served from 1964 to 1981. A curriculum vita and newspaper biography are noted in the folder inventory.
The Florence R. Crane papers document her activities as a civic leader in Ann Arbor and in Michigan and reflect her civic and political involvements. The papers cover the years 1949-1989 and include materials on Ann Arbor charter revision, housing, and zoning and planning activities; the Republican Party; the Michigan Corrections Commission; the University of Michigan; and other civic activities.
The Crane papers have been retained in their original order and arranged in five series: Ann Arbor Citizens' Council, Ann Arbor Citizen's Housing Committee, Ann Arbor City Council, Michigan Corrections Commission, Republican Party and Topical.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor Citizens' Council.; Ann Arbor (Mich.). Common Council.; Ann Arbor (Mich.). Housing Commission.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Crane, Florence R., 1911-; Municipal government--Michigan.; Republican Party (Mich.); Women in politics--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women civic leaders--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Civic leaders--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
corpname; Crane, Florence R., 1911-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Ann Arbor Citizens' Council
  The Ann Arbor Citizens' Council materials contain reports, citizens' petitions, pamphlets, newspaper clippings from 1949 to 1954, a 1962 "Report of Citizens' Council Municipal Charter Revision Committee," and a 1963 report on activities written by Florence Crane, Executive Committee Chair.
  - Charter Revision (Box 1)
  - Report,1962-1963 (Box 1)
- Ann Arbor Citizen's Housing Committee
  The Ann Arbor Citizen's Housing Committee folders include correspondence, minutes and agendas, c.1953-1954 and "Report of the Housing Survey of Ann Arbor," 1954.
  - Agendas,correspondence, minutes, c.1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - Report of the Housing Survey, 1954 (Box 1)
- Ann Arbor City Council
  The Ann Arbor City Council materials covers the years 1957 to 1959. A newspaper biography of Crane can be found in the 1957 folder and a curriculum vita in the 1958-59 folder.
  - Campaign, clippings, correspondence, pamphlets circa 1957 (Box 1)
  - Campaign, clippings, correspondence, pamphlets, curriculum vita, circa 1958 (Box 1)
- Michigan Corrections Commission
  The Michigan Corrections Commission materials include materials from 1964 to 1979. Correspondence has been placed in one folder, and reports and other materials have been placed in a second folder. Of special interest in the "Petitions and Reports" folder is a court action brought by feminist groups against the University of Michigan for discriminatory action in excluding women from a sociology course in penology co-offered with the Department of Correction and reports on conditions in Michigan prisons, particularly women's prisons. Information concerning inmate parole requests or medical and behavioral problems has been removed.
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Petitions, reports (Box 1)
- Republican Party
  The Republican Party materials include Republican special events from 1951 to 1956 and Ann Arbor Republican City Committee correspondence, budgets and meetings, 1953-1955.
  - Ann Arbor City Republican Committee, Correspondence, circa 1953 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor City Republican Committee, Correspondence, circa 1954 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor City Republican Committee, Agendas, Activities, circa 1955 (Box 1)
  - Special Events, GOP, circa 1951-1956 (Box 1)
- Topical
  The Topical materials include various civic activities of Crane.
  - Ann Arbor Chamber of Commerce-Report on Agency Space and Capital Needs, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Friends of the Ann Arbor Hands on Museum, Financial Reports, Membership, Minutes,1984-1988 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 1)
  - No Name Reading and Elbow Bending Club of Ann Arbor (Box 1)
  - Photoprints -- aSnapshot of Crane and her husband (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan. Faculty Women's Club (Box 1)